<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Emanuele D'Osualdo</title>
    <description>The fabulous homepage of Emanuele D'Osualdo
</description>
    <link>http://emanueledosualdo.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://emanueledosualdo.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2016 18:08:06 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2016 18:08:06 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>What is that weird animation on my homepage?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So nice of you to ask! What you are looking at is an example of the systems we study in Concurrency Theory. In short, it is an example of a mathematical formalisation of a simple internet protocol; the aim of our research is to design algorithms that can prove properties of these kinds of models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/feed.xml&quot; class=&quot;button primary&quot;&gt;Subscribe&lt;/a&gt;
If you’d like to know more, watch this space for an upcoming write-up about the π‑calculus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More precisely, the displayed animation is a visual simulation of the evolution of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%CE%A0-calculus&quot;&gt;π‑calculus&lt;/a&gt; program. The boxes are sequential processes, i.e. threads, and the dots are names, i.e. channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simulation on the homepage is running a fixed program modelling a server/client system. The orange boxes are the clients, the blue ones are servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote the simulator in JavaScript and &lt;a href=&quot;https://d3js.org/&quot;&gt;D3.js&lt;/a&gt; to support my presentation on the contents of &lt;a href=&quot;/research/#thesis&quot;&gt;my Ph.D. thesis&lt;/a&gt;. The code evolved from a simple prototype and I am in the process of rewriting it completely. Once it is in usable state I’ll post it on GitHub, so stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://emanueledosualdo.com/explain-picalc.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://emanueledosualdo.com/explain-picalc.html</guid>
        
        <category>picalculus</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
