<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Emanuele D'Osualdo</title>
    <description>The fabulous homepage of Emanuele D'Osualdo
</description>
    <link>http://emanueledosualdo.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://emanueledosualdo.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 19:51:56 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 19:51:56 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The art of the misspelling</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My name is Emanuele D’Osualdo.
I know what you are thinking, and I do not blame you.
Actually, let me get this straight from the start:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I hereby forgive you, fully and pre-emptively,
for misspelling or mispronouncing my name or surname.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, my name is long and complicated (although it has been pointed out to me that Polish names can be orders of magnitude more complicated),
but in fact I am always amused from the strange misspellings I collected during the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before going into that, if you are wondering about the pronunciation,
here is my name pronounced correctly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;audio src=&quot;/doc/name.mp3&quot; controls=&quot;controls&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/doc/name.mp3&quot; class=&quot;button&quot;&gt;
      Click here to play
      &lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-play&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/audio&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;misspellings-of-dosualdo&quot;&gt;Misspellings of D’Osualdo&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My surname is weird even to Italian ears. Common misspellings include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D’Osvaldo&lt;/strong&gt; (Osvaldo is an old-fashioned Italian name)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D’Osvualdo&lt;/strong&gt; (if you are not sure, put both)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D’Osvivaldo&lt;/strong&gt; (strangely reminiscent of Vivaldi)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gesualdo&lt;/strong&gt; (another Italian composer!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D’Osulado&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;d’odusldo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dosualvo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dosvalbo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dosvlaudo&lt;/strong&gt; — or something like this where it is clear that the one who typed it simply gave up after three letters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;d’Osualdo&lt;/strong&gt; or just &lt;strong&gt;Osualdo&lt;/strong&gt; — I get this a lot in Germany, where they seem to interpret the “D’” as an optional decoration. Main drawback: I may be listed under “O” in alphabetic order!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-apostrophe&quot;&gt;The apostrophe&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A separate category of misspellings concerns the apostrophe:
we are in 2016 and still computer systems systematically stumble when dealing with my surname.
The apostrophe is to an online form
what a mouse is to an elephant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;centered&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2016-11-02-the-art-of-the-misspelling/cyberman.gif&quot; /&gt; 
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2016-11-02-the-art-of-the-misspelling/apostrophe.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it is simply rejected, sometimes the apostrophe gets removed with arbitrary fixes such as replacing it with a space or removing the character altogether.
And these are the good cases. In others it simply makes the system fail because of improper handling of user-provided data.
Yes I am &lt;a href=&quot;http://xkcd.com/327/&quot;&gt;Little Bobby Tables&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;wide-image&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://xkcd.com/327/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/exploits_of_a_mom.png&quot; alt=&quot;Exploits of a mom (xkcd.com)&quot; title=&quot;Exploits of a mom (xkcd.com)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact it is the apostrophe in my surname that made me independently come up with my first SQL-injection exploit. Good times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Germany the problem is aggravated by the fact that the German language uses the apostrophe very rarely, so people just use the acute accent symbol ` instead, which is more easily found on keyboards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there’s my first name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-curse-of-emmanuelle&quot;&gt;The curse of Emmanuelle&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make things worse, my first name, &lt;em&gt;Emanuele&lt;/em&gt;, lends itself to all sorts of ambiguities and misspellings.
The list of similar, but distinct, names is long:
Emmanuele, Emmanuelle, Emanuelle, Manuel, Manuele, Manuelle…
To those you have to add the misspellings (once I got Emanuale).
Pronunciation is a further issue: at best I get something that resembles &lt;em&gt;manual&lt;/em&gt;, at worst I get some irrecognisable mash of &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;s, &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;s and &lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funniest story around my first name comes from my Erasmus in Turkey.
I arrive in Istanbul and go to my hostel.
They ask for my ID, start transcribing the data…when they stop at the name and start giggling.
Ok, fine, it’s a strange name, whatever, just give me the keys of the room.
After some rest, I go back to the reception and the guy starts giggling again after seeing me. Uh, ok, weird. I explore the surroundings, go back to the hostel. Now the receptionist is with a friend and as soon as I show up he says my name in a very refined attempt to signal to his friend that “This is the guy I told you about”. Ok, guy from the reception, I confront you: what’s so funny?!?
«Well…you know…when I was little…there was this, uhm, “movie”, you know the ones that they play late at night…it was called &lt;em&gt;Emmanuelle&lt;/em&gt;. Every Turk knows it!»
This is true, apparently “Emmanuelle” was a popular &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emmanuelle_(film)&quot;&gt;erotic movie from the seventies&lt;/a&gt;.
Except:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;centered&quot;&gt;THE MALE ITALIAN NAME EMANUELE&lt;br /&gt;
IS &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
THE FEMALE FRENCH NAME EMMANUELLE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beside the spelling and the different language,
the pronunciation is completely different.
Of course to Turkish ears the two are indistinguishable.
With obvious repercussions on my introductions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;- «Hello I am Murat»&lt;br /&gt;
- «Nice to meet you, I am…MANU»&lt;br /&gt;
[Friend who knew me from before]&lt;br /&gt;
- «“Manu”? No…tell him your full name!»&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, every time I introduced myself to a &lt;em&gt;male&lt;/em&gt; Turkish guy I got the giggles back!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- ## The worst list of nicknames on earth

Although people used many nicknames for me in the past---Ema, Emanu, Lele, Dosu---the one that I commonly use is Manu.
Feel free to use it! --&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://emanueledosualdo.com/blog/2016/the-art-of-the-misspelling.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://emanueledosualdo.com/blog/2016/the-art-of-the-misspelling.html</guid>
        
        <category>fun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What is that weird animation on my homepage?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So nice of you to ask! What you are looking at is an example of the systems we study in Concurrency Theory. In short, it is an example of a mathematical formalisation of a simple internet protocol; the aim of our research is to design algorithms that can prove properties of these kinds of models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;note&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/feed.xml&quot; class=&quot;button primary&quot;&gt;Subscribe&lt;/a&gt;
If you’d like to know more, watch this space for an upcoming write-up about the π‑calculus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More precisely, the displayed animation is a visual simulation of the evolution of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%CE%A0-calculus&quot;&gt;π‑calculus&lt;/a&gt; program. The boxes are sequential processes, i.e. threads, and the dots are names, i.e. channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simulation on the homepage is running a fixed program modelling a server/client system. The orange boxes are the clients, the blue ones are servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote the simulator in JavaScript and &lt;a href=&quot;https://d3js.org/&quot;&gt;D3.js&lt;/a&gt; to support my presentation on the contents of &lt;a href=&quot;/research/#thesis&quot;&gt;my Ph.D. thesis&lt;/a&gt;. The code evolved from a simple prototype and I am in the process of rewriting it completely. Once it is in usable state I’ll post it on GitHub, so stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://emanueledosualdo.com/explain-picalc.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://emanueledosualdo.com/explain-picalc.html</guid>
        
        <category>picalculus</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
